Guide to the Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums, 1477-1905 and undated RL.00628
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums
1477-1905 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jantz, Harold Stein, 1907-1987, collector
RL.00628
5 Linear Feet 170 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums, was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1996.
Biographical Note
Harold Jantz was a Professor of German literature at Northwestern, Johns Hopkins, and Duke Universities, and a collector of German baroque literature and German Americana.
Collection Overview
The Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums, 1477-1905 and undated, is arranged by size (each item numbered) and includes the following noncontiguous subgroups: Autograph Albums (1633-1857 and undated), Early Music Manuscripts (1818-1874 and undated), Early Manuscript Prayerbooks (1744-1801 and undated), and Early Manuscript Songbooks (1712-1896 and undated). These subgroups are described more fully below.
The collection consists primarily of bound manuscripts, many illustrated, from the 15th through the early 20th centuries. Most materials are in German or English, with some materials in French, Hebrew, Italian, Spanish, Swedish, Greek, or Latin. In addition to the above noted subgroups, the collection includes medical texts (nos. 28, 47, 77); historical chronicles, mostly German (nos. 25, 58, 59, 84, 127); and alchemical/astrological/occult treatises (nos. 9, 20, 53, 74, 114, 120, 122, 129, 148, 161, 165). Among the identified authors are Georg Fabricius (22), Edward Young (29), Sebastian Chiesa (33), Henry Marchant (49), Jacob Böhme (67), J.M. Firmenich (156), and Carl and Julius Dresel (117-119). Printed books, most with manuscript addenda, comprise approximately 10% of the collection.
The subgroup Autograph Albums (1633-1857 and undated) chiefly comprises bound volumes (guestbooks, Stammbücher) of 18th-and 19th-century German, English, and American provenance. These typically contain poems (many original), quotations, and maxims, as well as signatures. Many are illustrated and have laid-in mementoes. This group contains the following numbers from the main collection: 3 (J.C.Waechtler), 4 (Caspari), 5 and 6 (C.F.M. Timaus), 8 (a freemason), 11 ( E.D.), 60, 61, and 62 (Elizabeth J. Noble), 63 ( Miss Kate), 65 (Sarah T. Hopkins), 68 (Ebr. Denison), 69 ( Cornelia), 72 and 104 (Annie Mckay), 106 (Lucinda Olcott), 107 (Eliza Sabin), 108 (Emeline Ronnsville), 117 (Carl Dresel von Geisenheim) and 134.
The subgroup Early Music Manuscripts (1818-1874 and n.d) includes fife music, Spanish songs, a 19th century English tune book, and a vocal dialogue with text entitled Das Bauern Mädchen und der Stadt Junge, as well as works by Harriette Gould Bark, Johann Adolf Hasse, Georg Philipp Telemann, and Isaac C. Day. It comprises numbers 1, 7, 10, 48, 71, 116, 126, 136, and 141 of the main collection.
The subgroup Early Manuscript Prayerbooks (1744-1801 and undated) consists chiefly of 18th-century Roman Catholic prayerbooks and devotional exercises (including 3 copies of Crönung Mariae) in German and Latin. Many are illustrated. It includes numbers 17, 27, 30, 31, 34, 66, 81, 94, 101, and 131-133 of the main collection.
The subroup Early Manuscript Songbooks, (1712-1896 and undated) includes both sacred (chiefly Roman Catholic) and secular song texts without music. The collection contains some German hymns. Items 13, 24, 36, 73, 86, 87, and 139 of the main collection comprise this group. Numbers 86 and 87 are 19th-century transcriptions from the 16th-century Heidelberger Liederhandschrift (Cod. Pal. 343) and Wernigerode Liederhandschrift Zy 15.
Some items from the Jantz Collection have been cataloged separately. To locate these, search the catalog under author: Harold Jantz Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Separated Materials
Some items from the Jantz Collection have been cataloged separately. To locate these, search the catalog under author: Harold Jantz Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Alchemy -- Manuscripts; Astrology -- Manuscripts; Autograph albums; Prayer-books; Music -- Manuscripts; Occultism -- Manuscripts; Medicine -- Manuscripts; Chiesa, Sebastiano, d. 1678; Bèohme, Jakob, 1575-1624; Young, Edward, 1683-1765; Marchant, Henry, 1741-1796; Fabricius, Georg, 1516-1571; Firmenich-Richartz, Johannes Matthias, 1808-1889
- List of Bound Manuscripts
  Separated Materials
  Some items from the Jantz Collection have been cataloged separately. To locate these, search the catalog under author: Harold Jantz Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
  - English (1818?): Jacob Burditt, ed.: Music Book, manuscript; The Fifers Companion... (see Jantz's note concerning Issac Day contained in book) (Ms 1)
  - German/Latin (undated): Anon.: German/Latin Grammer/Style(?), Manuscript-bound (Ms 2)
  - German (1695ff.): J. C. Waechtler: A Guestbook [Stammbuch], various languages (German, French, Latin), Manuscript-bound (Ms 3)
  - German (1802ff.): Poems to a certain Herrn Caspari by his friends, Manuscript-bound (Ms 4)
  - German (1755ff., with insert from 1633): Anon.: A Guestbook [Stammbuch], Manuscript-softbound, drawings and watercolors (Ms 5)
  - German (1778ff.): C. F. M. Timaus (?) [Hannover]: Album, a Guestbook [Stammbuch] with entries, 1778-1783, various langagues (French, German, Latin, Greek), Manuscript-bound (Ms 6)
  - Spanish (undated): Anon.: Music Book, Manuscript-bound (Ms 7)
  - German (1789): Anon. (?-see 6th entry): A Guestbook [Stammbuch] (Freemasonry), Manuscript-bound (Ms 8)
  - German (1610): Anon.: Elucidatio Secretorum, (Alchemy), Manuscript-bound (Ms 9)
  - English (1874): Harriette Gould Bark: Music Book, (drawn lines, notes inserted), [note popular: "Jesus Loves Me"] (Ms 10)
  - German (1836): Lembert: Almanach dramatischer Spiele für das Jahr 1836, Wien: Franz Tendser, Printed book with manuscript emendations inserted by author(?) (Ms 12)
  - German (1844): Turn=Leider, Book: Munich: Franz Wild, 1844, Printed book with manuscript text and music notes (Ms 13)
  - German (1850-1880?): L.G. Silbercleit, ed./trans.: Robert Burns' Lieder und Balladen, Leipzig: Reclam, undated, Printed book (Ms 14)
  - French (undated): Anon.: Histoire du Palais Royal, Manuscript-bound (Ms 15)
  - German (1733ff.): Anon.(?): Louisel: Abschieds=Lieder, [Hernnhut poems], Manuscript-bound (Ms 16)
  - German (undated) and Latin (18th c.?): Anon.: Weis, die H.-Schütz-Engel zu Verehren (Ways to Honor the Guardian Angel), Manuscript-bound (Ms 17)
  - German (1790): L.F. Heuser: Gedichte: Erster Theil, Manuscript-bound (Ms 18)
  - Italian (1549-1550): Pietro D'Abano: Della Geomantia, First Part-Completely Manuscript; Second Part-Partially Printed (incl. Title Page), Partially ms. (Ms 19)
  - German (1685): Eireneo Philaletha [George Starkey, 1628-1665], Johann Lange, trans.: Kern der Alchemie (Leipzig: Valentin Adler, 1685), (The Prince Lichtenstein copy), Manuscript-bound, typed information sheet inside cover. (Ms 20)
  - German (1696): Johann Georg Graberr: Eine kürtze Eröffung und Anweisung der 3 Principien und Welten im Menschen, Manuscript-bound (Ms 21)
  - German (16th or 17th C.): G. Fabricius (1516-1571): German translation of his Latin: Historia von den Leiden und Sterben unsers Herren Jhesu Christi, Wie Man solches betrachten und bedencken soll... (To be sung both at night and during the day), Manuscript-bound (Ms 22)
  - German (1684): P. Joachim Stegbuecher: Geistliche Ubungen, Manuscript-bound (Ms 23)
  - German (1712): Gesänge (Religious Songs), Manuscript-bound (illustrated) (Ms 24)
  - German (1896 Nov.): Karl Scheffer: Inschriften und Legenden Halberstädter Bauten (1864), Manuscript copy (bound) by J. Schule (Ms 25)
  - German (1775?): Anon.: Sammlung einiger vermischten Nachrichten und Urkunden, Maurerey betreffend (also some English text), Manuscript-bound (Ms 26)
  - German (18th c. [1791??]): Anon.: Prayer Book, Manuscript-bound (Ms 27)
  - English (1884): Edward Young, [Samuel and Bernice Allinson]: Beauties of the Night Thoughts, at end of vol.: 1819 Burlington City, N.J. Prospectus (Allinson), Manuscript-bound (Ms 29)
  - German (undated): Elisebeta (Hardegg): Gebettbuch, illustrated, Manuscript-bound (Ms 30)
  - German (1791): Anon.: Gebettbuch, Manuscript-bound (Ms 31)
  - Italian (1720): Sebastiano Chiesa: Il Capitolo de Frati: Poema Eroico, Comico e Prurito Geniale Auttunale di Frá Tesabisano Sechia, Manuscript-bound (Ms 33)
  - German (1767): Anon.: Bett Buch (Prayer Book), Manuscript-bound (Ms 34)
  - German (1755): S.C.v.Z.: Historische Einleitung in die Kenntniß der Reiche und Staaten..., Breslaau: Johann Jacob Korn, 1755, mostly printed text, quite a few ms. leaves at end (Ms 35)
  - German (19th c., see p. 119): Algovia's Lieder, Manuscript-bound (Ms 36)
  - German (1852): Ihtak Kenhelsemib (?): Momus. zur Erheiterung: Scherz, Witz und Picanterien (some French text), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 37)
  - German (1725-1727): Einleitung zur neuesten Historie der Welt..., 3 volumes: Jena: Joh. Volckmar Marggrafen, 1725 (1723?)-1727, Printed books (Ms 38)
  - German (1803): Die kleine geistliche Harfe der Kinder Zions...(Song Book), Germantaun: Michael Billmeyer, 1803, 1st ed. (authorized by Mennonite communities), Printed book (Ms 39)
  - English (undated): Anon.: Elucidation of Biblical Texts (?), Manuscript-bound (Ms 40)
  - German (19th c.): August Klingemann (1777-1831): Faust, Book with inserted emendations by author over a number of years (Ms 41)
  - English (1750-1759): Thomas Wright (Durham): Pansophia or a General Regulation of Universal Knowledge, Manuscript-bound (Ms 42)
  - English (undated): Anon.: Elucidation of Biblical Texts, Manuscript-bound (Ms 43)
  - German (19th c.?): Anon.: Short Treatises and Poems, Manuscript-bound (Ms 44)
  - English (1834): Charles Cole: Political and Other Poems, Second Ed., London: W.C. Mantz, 1834, Printed book (Ms 45)
  - German (c. 1716-1720): Grüber (?), Manuscript-bound containing religious poems, parts of New Testament, etc., see Jantz's notes inside cover (Ms 46)
  - German (1651-1654): [Leip, Friedrich?]: Medical Manuscript, Partially bound (Ms 47)
  - German (1826): Anon.: Feurige Kohlen der aufsteigenden Liebesflammen..., Book and Manuscript (text and notes) (Ms 48)
  - English (1771ff.): Letters, etc. of Henry Marchant, Letters of Ezra Stiles to Benj. Franklin, Prof. Hahn (Utrecht), etc., copied by D. King 1864, Manuscript-bound (Ms 49)
  - German (ca. 1700): Anon.: Maria eine Zuflucht der Sinder und Trösterin der Betriebt (Volksschauspiel), Manuscript-bound (see description by Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger inside cover) (Ms 50)
  - German (1861??): ?: Abendteuer des Entspekter Dräßig...Book with many emendations by author (Ms 51)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Der getreue Ehegatte, Manuscript-bound (Ms 52)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Beschreibung der wahren göttlichen Magia, Manuscript-bound (Ms 53)
  - German (1801): F.P.(?): Die Seele vor ihrem Schöpfer, Manuscript-bound (Ms 54)
  - German (1764): Anon.: Auser-Lessenes Exempel Buech..., Manuscript-bound (see enclosed catalog description) (Ms 55)
  - English (ca. 1850): Anon.: Ledger with printed poems pasted in (and written poem on Comm. Perry), Manuscript-bound (Ms 56)
  - German (1839): Karl von Holtei: Almanach für Privat-Bühnen, Riga/Leipzig: Verlavgon Eduard Frantzen, mostly printed text, Manuscript emendations (by author?) to Dreiunddreißig Minuten in Grüneberg (Ms 57)
  - German/Latin (1477): Johan Carion: Chronica durch Magistrum Johan Carion..., mostly printed book but Latin/German Ms. from 1477 bound in at end (Ms 58)
  - German (1717?): Hans George Mokren (see 2nd Leaf: Schotte): Thüringischer und Mühlhausischer Chronicken Extract..., Manuscript-bound (Ms 59)
  - English (undated; 1845-one poem): The Scriptural Album with Floral Illustrations, a few poems, Manuscript-bound (Ms 60)
  - English (1834-1836): Album, Collection of Poems, Manuscript-bound (Ms 61)
  - English (ca. 1863ff.): [M.A. Jennings?]: A Few Thoughts in Verse, Manuscript-bound (Ms 64)
  - German (1763): Anon.: Prayer Book, Printed illustrations, Manuscript (text)-bound (Ms 66)
  - English (1710): John Holborn: Various (copied) texts of Jacob Boehme, etc., Manuscript-bound, see Jantz's notes inside cover (Ms 67)
  - English (May 1821ff.): Ebr. Denison's Collection of poems (by friends?), Manuscript-partially bound (Ms 68)
  - English (1844ff.): Poems by Jonathan Tilson (see Jantz's note inside cover), Manuscript-bound (Ms 70)
  - English (undated [19th c.?]): Anon.: Music notebook, several texts, Manuscript-bound (Ms 71)
  - English (undated [19th c.]): Anon.: Collection of poems, Manuscript-bound (Ms 72)
  - English (undated [18th c.]): Anon.: Copies of poems, sayings, etc., Manuscript-bound (Ms 73)
  - Latin (1665): [Maurizio Fieschi: Comitis de Flisco Decas de Facto...astrological treatise, Manuscript-bound (Ms 74)
  - German (1905): Rudolf Réer: Die Vergangenheit der Rosenau, Manuscript-bound (Ms 75)
  - German (1800): Anon.: Wilhelm Brau, oder die Folgen des Franzosischen Kriegs, Erster Theil, Manuscript-bound (Ms 76)
  - German (ca. 1701): Anon.(?): Probier: Küntz: und Schmeltz Büches(?), (Apothecary Matters), Manuscript-bound (Ms 77)
  - German (1748): Johann Christian Edelmann: Die andere Epistel St. Harenbergs an Johann Christian Edelmann, Manuscript-bound (Ms 78)
  - German (1776): Das gelehrte Teutschland oder Lexikon der jeztlebenden Teutschen Schriftsteller angefangen von Georg Christoph Hamberger, fortgesetzt von Johann Georg Meusel, Lemgo: Meyersche Buchhandlung, 1776, 3rd ed., Printed book with some manuscript augmentations/emendations (Ms 79)
  - German (1831): Einschreibebuch für H. H. Graue, Ledger-wts./measures, Manuscript-bound (Ms 80)
  - German (1789): Tobias Oßwald: Der wohlriechende Blumen-Garten...(Prayer Book), Manuscript-bound (Ms 81)
  - German (1576?-see p. 301): Anon.: Lebensbeschreibung des Ritters Görz von Berlichingen, manuscript bound, (see letter from Dr. Helgard Ulmschneider and pp. 42-43 of Ulmschneider's Book: Götz von Berlichingen: Mein Fehd und Handlungen, Sigmaringen, 1981) (Ms 82)
  - German (undated): Der ächte Eidsgenoß: Eine wöchentliche Sittenschrift: Dritten Jahrgang, Manuscript-bound (with printed t.p.) (from Friedrich Gundolf's library with his signature Basel 1930) (Ms 83)
  - German (1796): Joh. Dan. Pohle: Allerleÿ merkwürdige Sachen welche seit dem Anfange des 1793 sten Jahres in der Gegend des Erfurthischen Gebieths vorgefallen sind, Manuscript-bound (Ms 84)
  - German (1852): Anon.: Seereise eines fahrenden Malers von Amsterdam nach Constantinopel, Manuscript-bound (Ms 85)
  - German (1895): R. Wolfgang: Auszüge Aus dem Cod. Pal. 343 (Liederhandschrift d. XVI Jhhs.), Copiert 12-I-95 - 14-III-95 (see Deutsche Texte des Mittelalters, Bd. V Berlin, 1905), Manuscript-bound (Ms 86)
  - German (1896): R. Wolfgang: Abschrift der Wernigeroder Liederhandschrift Zg 15, Saec. XVI-XVII, Manuscript-bound (Ms 87)
  - German (undated [19th c.?]): Johann Polischanzky: Vergies mein nicht, Manuscript-bound (Ms 88)
  - Latin (with some German)(undated [18th c.]): Anon.: A Deo sit felicis anni avspicivm, Manuscript-bound (Ms 89)
  - French (1815ff.): Lettres de Madame Bertrand (References to Napoleon), Manuscript-bound (Ms 90)
  - Italian (1555): G. Postello (?): Le Prime Nove del Altro Mondo...La Vergine Venetiana, Manuscript-bound (Ms 91)
  - German (1778): Anon.: Geschichte des berühmten Portugisischen Juden Duliz, Manuscript-bound (Ms 92)
  - German (1830): Anon.: Biblische Archäologie, Manuscript-bound (Ms 93)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Himmlische Herzenshoffnung, Manuscript-bound (Ms 94)
  - German (ca. 1720): Collection of six copies of original manuscripts, Manuscript-bound (see description of ms. inside cover) (Ms 95)
  - English (mid 18th c.): Manuscripts of the late Richard Gouch, esq., Partially bound (Ms 96)
  - German (1780-1794): Abbe Andreas Stütz: 108 poems and plays, Manuscript-bound, see description enclosed (Ms 97)
  - German (1835): Ferdinand v. d. Golz: Sketches, maps, etc., Christmas gift for his parents, Manuscript-bound (Ms 98)
  - English (1836): William Potter(?): Journal: Chemistry, botany, recipes, etc., Manuscript-bound, 2 vols. (Ms 99)
  - German (1719): Anon.: Travel journal (1719-1724), Manuscript-bound (Ms 100)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Kurtze Andachtsübungen...(Prayer Book), Manuscript-bound (Ms 101)
  - English (before 1806): T. Wright: Maxims, Queries, and Apophthegms, Manuscript-bound. From the library of Sir W. Betham with his ownership mark. Recorded in the auction of by R H Evans, London, 1830 as lot 402; and subsequently in Thorpe's Catalogue of Manuscripts 1830, as item 14761. (Ms 102)
  - German (1844?-see p. 297; 1863?-see title page): ?: Hamlet: Prinz von Dänemark (Play), Manuscript-bound (Ms 103)
  - English (1857): M.L. King (Montreal) to Annie Mackay: Poems to A. Mackay from friends, Manuscript-bound (Ms 104)
  - English (1830's and 1840's): Ruth Schuyler (?): Poems, Manuscript-bound (Ms 105)
  - English (1826ff.): Poems written for Lucinda Olcott, Manuscript-bound (Ms 106)
  - English (1826ff.): Poems written for Eliza Sabin, Manuscript-bound (Ms 107)
  - English (1827ff.): Poems for Emeline Ronnsville, Manuscript-bound (Ms 108)
  - English (? [19th c.]): Diary of William Whiteway from December, 1618 to March, 1634 (copied by J.B. Baxter?), Manuscript-bound (Ms 109)
  - German (1800): Wenzl Benedikt Sack: Sammlung verschiedener poetischer Werke, Manuscript-bound (Ms 110)
  - English (?[19th c.?; one poem 1819]): John Brown: Fantasies in Rhyme, Manuscript-bound (Ms 111)
  - English (1851): Augustus Griffin: Rhymes (written down for his grandson), dating back to 1795, Manuscrip- bound (Ms 112)
  - German/Latin (undated): Anon.: vom Ursprung der Brüder Vom Teutschen Hauß...Manuscript-beautifully bound (Ms 113)
  - English (undated): Anon.: A novel on spiritualism, Manuscript-softbound (typed) (Ms 114)
  - Hebrew (undated): ?: Manuscript-bound, 11 leaves (Ms 115)
  - Latin (undated [19th c.?]): I.A. Hasse: Puer Natus (musical composition), Manuscript-bound (Ms 116)
  - German (1844ff.): Carl Dresel von Geisenheim: Album with poems, sayings, etc. (note Hoffmann von Fallersleben), Manuscript-bound (Ms 117)
  - German (1841ff.): Gedichte von Julius Dresel, Manuscript-bound (Ms 118)
  - German (1849ff.), Letters of Carl Dresel-Tenge, Manuscript-bound (Ms 119)
  - English (c. 1903): A.E.F. Horniman, trans.: Trans. of G.F. Borri's, The Key of the Cabinet of the Cavaliere G.F. Borri, typewritten, bound manuscript (see description inside cover) (Ms 120)
  - English (20th c.): ?: Forty-nine holograph letters of together eighty-one pages written by John Quincy Adams and one letter written by his secretary T. Welsh between 1797 April 2 and 1801 July 5, typed, Bound Manuscript (Ms 121)
  - Latin (undated): Anon.: Martinitz, Bernard von.: Quadratsra Circuli Stegano Graphici, Manuscript-bound (Ms 122)
  - Latin (1611?): Anon.: Primi et Primigenii/Germanicae Gentis Maiores et Progenitores Eiusdem..., Manuscipt-bound (Ms 123)
  - Latin (undated [late 18th-early 19th?]): ?: Astrological/Biblical Treatises, 2 volumes (some Hebrew), Manuscript-bound (Ms 124)
  - English (1820s-1830s): Anon.: Ledger, Manuscript-bound (Ms 125)
  - English (18th c.): Copy of Telemann's Concerto in C Major for recorder and strings, Manuscript-bound (Ms 126)
  - German (Late 16th c.): Anon.: Chronicle of Germany dating back to 5th C., Manuscript-bound (Ms 127)
  - English (1859?): Anon.: Recollections and Reminiscences (On Board a Clipper Ship Headed for China), Manuscript-bound and unbound earlier [first?] draft (Ms 128)
  - Latin (1701): Jacob Utecht: Opus Naturae et Artis..., (Alchemy), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 129)
  - German (17th c.): Matthias Abele (1616 or 18-1677): Metamorphosis Telae Judiciariae (Seltzame Gerichts-Händel), Manuscript-fragment (Ms 130)
  - German (1744): Anon.: Krönung Mariae der 12 Sternen genannt, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 131)
  - German (1744): Anon.: Krönung Mariae der 12 Sternen genannt (Copy 2), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 132)
  - German (1744?): Anon.: Krönung Mariae der 12 Sternen genant (Copy 3), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 133)
  - English (185?): [Dalston?]: Anecdotes and jokes, Manuscript-bound (Ms 135)
  - English (undated): Isaac C. Day: Music book, Manuscript-bound (Ms 136)
  - English (1847): Anon.: Classroom lecture notes of Profs. Silliman's and Olmsted's classes (Ms 137)
  - German (1788): Zimmermännische Schrift über Friedr[ich] des Großen, Unbound Manuscript (Göttingen) (Ms 138)
  - German (undated [18th c.?]): Anon.: 77 pages of Lieder and index, Manuscript-bound (Ms 139)
  - German (undated): Pepi Raics's(?) Ausgewählte Gedichte, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 140)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Das Bauern-Mädchen und der Stadt Junge, Unbound manuscript, music and text (Ms 141)
  - German (Swiss?)(undated): Leopold Koppelhuber et al.: Der Budl-Haubn-Teufel, et al., Unbound Manuscript (Ms 142)
  - German (undated): Einblattdrucke, mss. and fragments (Ms 143)
  - German (1823?): T.F. Castellÿ: Gabriele, Partial manuscript (first 3 leaves), bound, mostly printed text (Ms 144)
  - German (31. VIII. 1838): Friedrich Halm: Der Adept: Trauerspiel in 5 Aufzügen, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 145)
  - German (1820): Adolf Bäuerle: Die Falsche Prima Donna, Pesth: Hartlebens Verlag, with emendations (by author?), Printed (Ms 146)
  - Kaiser: Die Schule des Armen, printed (Ms 147)
  - German (1631): Abraham von Franc...?: Saephiriel (himmlisches Licht und magischer Bericht: die Geheimnisse der Zahlen), Manuscript-bound (Ms 148)
  - German (1672): Anon.: Dienstbarkeit zwischen denen Lieben Abent Music...(A Play), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 149)
  - German (undated): Anon.: Poem: So geht der Feldzug wieder An, Unbound manuscript (Ms 150)
  - German (1681): Anon.: Tragico Comoedia genant, Die siegende Unschuldt (play), Unbound manuscript (Ms 151)
  - German (Swiss?)(undated): [Leopold Koppelhuber?]: Der Budelhaubn-Toifl, Unbound Manuscript (Ms 152)
  - English (1829): Compositions read before The Society of Mutual Instruction: by Ebr. Denison, Manuscript-Partially softbound (Ms 153)
  - English (1829): Lectures in Science by Ebr. Denison, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 154)
  - English (1821-1823): Journal (Anon.), Jantz's note: by an apprentice of Middletown, Conn., Manuscript-softbound (Ms 155)
  - German (pre-1840): J.M. Firmenich (1808-1884): Clotilda Montalvi, (published 1840), Manuscript-softbound (Ms 156)
  - German (18th c./19th c.): Goethe and Falk autographs and a 19th c. Goethe Apocryphal poem (Ms 157)
  - English (1802): Joseph Strong: Sermon...General Election, 1802, printed (Ms 158)
  - German (1858): Knut Jungbohn Clement: Die Bekehrung Englands..., Manuscript-softbound (Ms 159)
  - Spanish (undated): Anon.: Religious treatise, Softbound manuscript (Vellun) (Ms 160)
  - German (1790): [Georgius Clottus(?)]: Von des Goldes Anfang...Unbound manuscript (Ms 161)
  - English (1851): Ebr. Denison Jr. (?): Philosopy, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 162)
  - English (undated, 19th c.): Anon.: Notes on Goethe, Unbound manuscript (Ms 163)
  - German (ca. 1810): Andegar Grundfest von Braunschweig: Geschichte der Fürstlichen Aebte zu Kempten, Manuscript-bound (Ms 164)
  - German (undated, [18th c.?]): Anon.: Citation derer sieben Planeten und anderer Geister durch die magischen Bilder (Astrological), Manuscript-bound (Ms 165)
  - German (1851): Copy of Goethe's Faust, Manuscript-softbound (Ms 166)